<document uuid="CIV0KH8uIuCBLp8kRgRJI">
<meta>
<copyright>CC0/PD. No rights reserved</copyright>
<source url="https://standardebooks.org/ebooks/arthur-conan-doyle/the-adventures-of-sherlock-holmes">Standard Ebooks</source>
<title>A Scandal in Bohemia</title>
</meta>
<chapter>
<chapter>
<meta>
<title n="I"/>
</meta>
<p>षर्लोक-होम्सस्य कृते सा नार्युत्तमा। मत्पुरतः तु सः ताम् अन्येन केनापि नाम्ना न उल्लेखितवान् अभूत्। होम्सस्य दृष्ट्यां सा सर्वासु स्त्रीषु अग्रगण्या, ताभ्यः परा अपि। ऐरीन्-आड्लरं प्रति तस्य मनसि प्रेम-सदृशं भावम् आसीत् इति तु न। सर्वाः भावनाः विशेषतः प्रीतिः तस्य भावनाशून्ययाः निपुणायाः समतुलितयाः बुद्ध्याः विरुद्धाः। मन्ये अहं यत् सः विश्वस्य सर्वोत्तमं तर्क-अवलोकन-यन्त्रम्। किन्तु प्रेमि-रूपेण तस्य स्थानं नास्ति। करुणा-प्रेम-सदृशानां भावानां विषये केवलम् उपहासेन वदति। प्रेक्षकाणां कृते तु भावनाः अद्भुताः यतोहि ताः मानवस्य उद्देशान् कार्याणि च अनावरेयुः। किन्तु तर्क-विशारदस्य कृते तु स्वीये, सूक्ष्मे, उत्कृष्टतया व्यवस्थीकृते, स्वभावे ईदृशानि अतिक्रमणानि प्रवेष्टुम् अनुमतानि चेत् बुद्धि-संबद्ध-परिणामानाम् उपरि शङ्कां जनयन् विक्षेपकः उत्पद्यते। सूक्ष्म-यन्त्रे कल्मषं वा उच्च-शक्ति-दृष्टिकाचे छेदाः अपि तावत् पर्यन्तं न बाधन्ते यावत् पर्यन्तं होम्स-सदृशस्य स्वभावे गाढभावस्य प्रवेशः। किन्तु तस्य कृते केवलम् एकैव स्त्री या अभूत् दिवङ्गता कुप्रसिद्धा ऐरीन्-आड्लरः।</p>
<p>तदा होम्सस्य दर्शनं मम विरलम् अभूत्। मद्-विवाहकारणात् आवां दूरीभुतौ। मम सम्पूर्ण-सुखं, नूतन-यजमानं परितः उत्पन्नाः सांसारिक-विषयाः च मम पूर्णं ध्यानम् आकर्षितवन्तः अभूवन् किन्तु रूढि-मुक्त-मनसा समाजस्य प्रत्येकं रूपं द्विषन् होम्सः इदानीमपि बेकर्-वीथ्याम् एव निवसन् अस्ति यत्र अहं पुरा होम्सेन सह निवासं कृतवान् अभूवम् तत्र एव होम्सः पुरातन-ग्रन्थानाम् अधः मग्नः अभूत्,   एकवारं महत्त्वाकाङ्क्षा-द्रव्यम् आस्वादयन्, अपरं तु कोकेन्-मादकद्रव्यम्, एकपक्षतः द्रव्यास्वादनात् निद्रालुत्वं लभमानः, अपरपक्षतः तु स्वीयस्य उत्साह-पूर्ण-स्वभावस्य दृढत्वम्। अपराधस्य अध्ययने इदानीमपि गम्भीरतया मग्नः सः स्वीयं बुद्धि-बलम्, स्वकीयाः अवलोकन-शक्तीः च उपयुज्य सङ्केतान् अनुसरन् आधिकारिक-आरक्षक-भटैः "त्यक्ताशाः" इति घोषितानां त्यक्तानां रहस्य-घटनानां समाधानं लब्धुं कार्यरतः। काले काले होम्सस्य गतिविधीनां विषये अस्पष्टतया श्रुतवान् अभूवम् - ओडेसा-नगरे ट्रेपोफ़-हत्या-विषये आह्वानं, श्रीलङ्कायां गोकर्णे आट्किन्सन्-भ्रात्रोः कुख्यातायाः दुःखद-घटनायाः समाधानं, होलाण्ड-देशस्य राज-कुटुम्बस्य नियोगस्य सूक्ष्मतया सफलतया समाधानं च। इमे विषयाः मया केवलं समाचार-माध्यमे सर्वैः पाठकैः सह सम्विभाजिताः, किन्तु इमान् कार्यकलापान् अतिरिच्य मम पूर्व-मित्रस्य सहचरस्य विषये मम ज्ञानं न्यूनम्।</p>
<p>कस्मिंश्चन नक्ते (अष्टाशीत्युत्तराष्टदशतमे वर्षे मार्च्-मासे विंशे दिवसे) रोगिनः गृहात् स्वगृहं प्रति गमनस्य काले (इतः पूर्वं प्रजावैद्य-सेवां पुनरारब्धवान्) बेकर्-वीथिद्वारा गतवान् अभूवम्। यस्य द्वारस्य सम्बन्धः सदा मम मनसि रक्ताध्ययनस्य निन्द्य-घटनैः, मदीयेन प्रेमालापेन च भवेत् तस्य सुस्मृतस्य द्वारस्य समीपे एव गत्वा होम्सं, कथं सः स्वीयाः  अद्भुत-शक्तीः उपयुज्यते इति च द्रष्टुं तीव्रेच्छा उत्पन्ना। तस्य कक्षाः प्रदीप्ताः अभूवन् एवं च यदाहम् उपरि दृष्टवान् अभूवं तदा तस्य उन्नतस्य कृशस्य कायस्य प्रतिच्छाया द्विवारम् आवरणस्य पृष्ठतः दृष्टा। हस्तौ च पृष्ठे संयत्य शिरः वक्षस्स्थल-पर्यन्तं नत्वा सः कक्षे इतस्ततः वेगेन पादचालनं कुर्वन् अभूत्। तस्य सर्वां मनोदशां सर्वम् अभ्यासं च जानन् अहं तस्य अभिवृत्तिना गत्या च किं जायमानमिति अवागमम्। पुनः कार्यरतः अभूत् सः। मादक-द्रव्य-मादात् जागरितः सः नूतन-समस्या-समाधाने मग्नः। घण्टानादम् कृतवान् अहं मम पूर्व-कक्षं प्रति नीतः।</p>
<p>तस्य व्यवहारः उल्लासपूर्णः नासीत्। विरलः एव, किन्तु मन्ये यत् सः प्रसन्नः आसीत् मम आगमनेन। विना सम्भाषणं किन्तु मैत्री-दृष्ट्या आसन्दं निर्दिश्य धूमवर्तीणां पेटिकां मां प्रति क्षिप्त्वा मद्य-पेठिकां विक्षारपान-यन्त्रं चापि निरदिक्षत्। ततः सः अग्निकुण्ड-पुरतः स्थित्वा स्वीय-स्वाभाविक्या परीक्षणात्मक-दृष्ट्या मां पश्यति स्म।</p>
<p>होल्म्सः प्रावोचत् - "विवाहः तुभ्यं युक्तः भवति। भाति मे वाट्सन यत् अस्मद्-विगतमेलनपेक्षया तव भारः सार्ध-त्रिकिलोपरिमितेन वर्धितः"</p>
<p>केवलं त्रिकिलोपरिमितः इति प्रत्यवोचत्।</p>
<p>"खलु! किञ्चित् अधिकमिति मया चिन्तनीयम् अभूत्। किञ्चिदेव इति मन्ये अहं वाट्सन। पुनः भैषज्यम् आचरसि इति मया लक्षितम्। पुनः कार्यम् आरब्धाः इति न माम् अवोचः।"</p>
<p>"अथ, कथं जानासि?"</p>
<p>"पश्यामि अनुमिनोमि च। कथं जाने यत् त्वम् अद्यतने काले आर्द्रः सन् विहरति एवं च तव सेविका अतीव असावधाना अक्षमा च?"</p>
<p>"भोः होम्स अति इदम्!" इति अवदम्। "केभ्यश्चन शताब्देभ्यः पूर्वं त्वं जीवितः चेत् तव मायाजाल-कारणात् सजीव-दहनम् अवश्यम् अभविष्यत्। सत्यं यत् बुधवासरे ग्राम्यक्षेत्रे भ्रमित्वा अव्यवस्थः सन् गृहं प्रत्यागमं किन्तु वस्त्रेषु परिवर्तितेषु सत्सु कथम् अभ्यूहितवान् अभूः इति न चिन्तयितुं शक्नोमि। सेविका-विषये कथयामि यत् सा मेरी-जेन् असंशोधनीया। अतः मम भार्या तस्यै कार्य-निष्कासन-सूचनाम् अदात्। किन्तु त्वया कथम् इदं परिज्ञातम् इति न अवगच्छामि।”</p>
<p>किञ्चित् हसित्वा स्वीय-दीर्घ-अस्थिर-हस्तौ अघर्षीत् होम्सः।</p>
<p>बहु सरलम् एव इति होल्म्सः उदतारीत्। "नेत्रौ मां वदतः यत् वाम-पादुकायां यत्र अग्नि-प्रकाशः पतति तत्र पादुक-चर्मणि समान्तर-छिन्न-रेखाः विद्यन्ते। स्पष्टं यत् शुष्क-पङ्कं निष्कासयितुं कश्चन विना चिन्तनं पादुका-तल-सीमां परितः अघर्षीत् होम्सः। एवंविधम् अवगतं मया यत् असमीचिने वातावरणे व्यहार्षीः, लन्दनीय-सेविकासु काञ्चित् दुर्बिद्धिं सेविकाम् अलब्धाः च। कथं तव भैषज्यकार्यविषये ज्ञातवान् अभूवम्? यदि कोऽपि सज्जनः मम कक्षे जम्बु-वम्रलम्य-गन्धेन सह आगच्छति, यस्य दक्षिण-तर्जन्यां रजत-भूयीयस्य कृष्ण-वर्णीय-बिन्दुः विद्यते, एवं च उच्च-शिरस्त्रस्य दक्षिण-भागे प्रफुल्लता वर्तते, यत्र स्पन्द-मापिनी निगूढा अस्ति, तर्हि सः वैद्यः इति न अवगच्छामि चेत् अहं मूर्खः।”</p>
<p>सरलानुमानः इति हसितुं विवशीभूतः अभूवम्। टिप्पणीम् अकार्षं यत् "यदा तव कारणानि शृणोमि तदा बहु सरलमिति भाति मे, मया कर्तुं शक्यते इति चिन्तयामि अपि। किन्तु विवरण-समये प्रत्येक-सोपाने कारण-उल्लेखात् पूर्वं विमूढः भवामि। किन्तु मन्ये अहं यत् मम नेत्रशक्तिः त्वादृशी एव।"</p>
<p>धूम्रवर्तिकाम् ज्वालयित्वा आसन्दे उपविश्य "एवमेव!" इति सः प्रत्यवादीत्। "त्वं पश्यसि, किन्तु नावलोकयसि। दर्शनावलोकनयोः भेदः सुस्पष्टः। उदाहरणतः, प्रधानकक्षात् आरभ्य इमं कक्षं यावत् यानि सोपानानि सन्ति, तानि त्वया बहुवारं दृष्टानि, किल?"</p>
<p>"आम्! बहुवारमेव।"</p>
<p>"कतिवारम्?"</p>
<p>"प्रायः शतवारम्?"</p>
<p>"अस्तु! वद कति?"</p>
<p>"कति? न जाने।"</p>
<p>"एवमेव! न त्वयावलोकितम्, केवलं तव दृष्टिपथमागतम्। अयमेव मम तर्कः। सप्तदश सोपानानि सन्तीति जाने, यतोहि मया तानि दृष्टान्यवलोकितानि च। अस्तु! ईदृश्यो लघुसमस्यास्तुभ्यं रोचन्ते किल? अपि च, मम तुच्छानुभवानामङ्कनं कर्तुं सक्षमस्त्वम्। अस्मिन् विषये तव रुचिः उत्पद्येतेति मन्ये।" इत्यवोचद् होम्सः। ततः होम्सः उत्पीठिकातः स्थूलम् उद्घाटितं पाटलारञ्जितं पत्रं मह्यं क्षिप्तवान् अभूत्। "पत्रवाहकः इदम् अदात्। कृपया उच्चैः पठ," इत्यवादीत्।</p>
<p>पत्रे तिथिः वा गृह-सङ्केतः वा हस्ताक्षरः वा न अभूत्।</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"आगमिष्यति भवतः दर्शनार्थम् अद्य रात्रौ कश्चन सज्जनः अत्यन्त-महत्त्वपूर्ण-विषये भवता सह मन्त्रणार्थम्। कस्यचन युरोपीय-राज-कुटुम्बस्य कृते भवता कृता सद्यःकालीन-सेवा निवेदयति यत् भवान् तेषां विषयाणां व्यवहारे विश्वासयोग्यः येषां महत्त्वम् अतिशयकथनं न शक्यते। भवद्विषये प्राप्ता इयं सूचना सर्वतः। तस्यां होरायां भवत्कक्षे एव भवतु तथा च अभ्यागतः मुखछादनं धारयित्वा आगमिष्यति चेत् अन्यथा मा चिन्तयतु।"</p></blockquote>
<p>"इदं तु रहस्यमयम्। तवानुसारं कोऽस्यार्थः?" इति टिप्पणीम् अकार्षम्।</p>
<p>"अधुनापि कोऽपि दातांशो मम पार्श्वे नास्ति। दातांशलाभात् पूर्वम् अनुमानकरणं हि महद्दोषाय। यतो हि तत्त्वानुसारम् अनुमानपरिवर्तनस्थाने, स्वानुमानानुसारं तत्त्व-विकारः जायेत। किन्तु लिखितस्य विषये कः विचारस्तव?"</p>
<p>कर्गदस्य, हस्तलेखस्य च परीक्षां सावधानतया अकार्षीम्।</p>
<p>मित्रस्य पद्धतिम् अनुसृत्य अवोचं यत् "लेखकः तु धनिकः इति प्रतीयते। ईदृशस्य कागदस्य मूल्यं बृहदेव। विचित्रं यत् बहु दृढं हृष्टं च।"</p>
<p>"विचित्रमेव। आङ्ग्ल-देशे न लभ्यते इदं कागदम्। इदं प्रकाशस्य समक्षे धारय।" इति होम्सः अवोचत्।</p>
<p>एवं कृत्वा बृहता <i>E</i>-अक्षरेण सह लघू <i>g</i>-अक्षरौ, <i>P</i>-अक्षरौ, बृहता <i>G</i>-अक्षरेण सह कागदस्य सूत्रे व्यूतम् लघु <i>t</i>-अक्षरम् च अदर्शम्।</p>
<p>"किम् अवगतं त्वया?" इति होम्सेन उक्तम्।</p>
<p>"निःसंशयं कारकस्य नाम उत वा गुम्फाक्षरम्।"</p>
<p>"नहि! नहि! <i>G'</i> इत्यनेन <i>t</i> इत्यस्य अर्थः अस्ति 'गिसेल्षाफ़्ट्', जर्मनी-भाषायाम् 'निगमः' इति। यथा आङ्ग्ल-भाषायां 'Co.'। <i>P</i>, इत्युक्ते 'पपीयर्'। ‘Eg.’ इत्यस्य कृते अस्मदीय महाद्वीप-वाचिकपत्त्रे अन्वेषणं कर्तव्यम्।" प्रकोष्ठातः स्थूलं पिङ्गल-वर्णीयं पुस्तकं गृहीतवान् होम्सः। "Eglow, Eglonitz— अत्र अस्ति, Egria. इति। बोहीयिमा इत्यस्मिन् जर्मनी-भाषिणि देशे कार्ल्स्बाड्-नगरात् अनतिदूरे स्थितं नगरम्। 'लक्षणीयं यत् अत्र वालन्ष्टैनस्य मृत्युः जातः तथा च बह्व्यः काच-कागद-निर्मान-शालाः सन्ति।' हह मित्र! अवगम्यते किम्?" इति अवोचत् होम्सः। तस्य नेत्रे प्रकाशिते जाते तथा च सः स्वीय-धूम्रवर्तिकातः विजयस्य आनन्देन बृहन्तं नील-वर्णीय-मेघं विमोचितवान् अभूत्।</p>
<p>कागदम् इदम् बोहीमियायां निर्मितम् इति अवदम्।</p>
<p>“सत्यम्। अस्य वाक्यस्य विचित्रा रचना लक्षणीया - 'भवद्विषये प्राप्ता इयं सूचना सर्वतः।' फ्रेञ्च्-देशीयः वा रष्या-देशीयः वा एतावत् न लिखेत्। जर्मनीयः अनया रीत्या लिखति। अयं मुखावरण-धारकः बोहीमिया-कागदे लिखन् जर्मनीयः किं वाञ्छति इति ज्ञातुम् एव शेषम्। अहो! अस्मदीयान् सर्वान् सन्देहान् दूरीकर्तुमेव इदानीम् आगच्छन् अस्ति।"</p>
<p>तस्य सम्भाषण-समये एव अश्व-पाद-शब्दानां, मार्गोपान्तेन सह चक्राणां घर्षणस्य च तीव्र-ध्वनिः श्रुता अभूत् यस्याः अनन्तरं द्वारे घण्टा-नादं जातम्।</p>
<p>"द्वयस्य ध्वनिः श्रूयते" इति होम्सः अवोचत्। वातायानतः दृष्ट्वा "आम्" इति अवोचत्। होम्सः सम्भाषणम् अनुवर्तितवान् अभूत् - "तत् वाहनं साधु एव, हयद्वयमपि। "हयद्वयं बहुमूल्यमेव। अस्मिन् प्रकरणे बहु धनमस्ति लभ्येत वाट्सन! अन्यत् किमपि स्यात् वा न वा।"</p>
<p>"गन्तव्यं स्यात् मया।"</p>
<p>"नैव भिषग्वर्य। अत्रैव तिष्ठ। विना मम इतिहासकारं कथं मे जीवितम्। अपिच रुचिकरम् स्यात् इदं प्रकरणम्। अनुपतिष्ठेः चेत् दौर्भाग्यम् एव।"</p>
<p>"किन्तु तव ग्राहकः-"</p>
<p>"चिन्ता मास्तु। तव साहाय्यं मह्यम् आवश्यकम् स्यात्, तस्मै अपि। अधुना सः आगच्छति। आसन्दं स्वीकृत्य भिषग्वर्य पूर्णतया अवधानं दद।"</p>
<p>मन्दं हृष्टं पदं यत् सोपानपथः उपकक्षतः च श्रुतम् तत् द्वारस्य पुरतः स्थगितं जातम्। तत् पश्चात् द्वारे उच्चैः आधिकारिकी ध्वनिः श्रुता।</p>
<p>"प्रविशतु!" इति होम्सः अवोचत्।</p>
<p>प्रविष्टस्य नरस्य औनत्यं षड्-पाद-षडङ्गुल-परिमितात् न्यूनं न स्यात्, तस्य वक्षस्स्थलम् अङ्गानि च भीमसेन-सदृशानि अभूवन्। तस्य परिधानं समृद्ध्या आढ्यम् अभूत्, या (समृद्धिः) आङ्ग्लदेशे कुरुचिः इति अवलोक्येत। अस्त्रखान-लोम-चर्मणः स्थूल-पट्टाः अग्रे बाहुवस्त्रस्योपरि च धृताः। बाह्वोः उपरि ज्वाला-वर्णीय-कौशेय-स्तर-युक्तः विनील-वर्णीय-प्रावारः कण्ठे एक-ज्वलित-वैडूर्य-युक्तेन खादिना बद्धः। चरण-जङ्घापिण्डी-मध्ये अर्ध-दूरे भ्रमपादिका-द्वयं धृतं अभूत्। भ्रमपादिकाद्वयस्य उपरितन-भागौ घन-पिङ्गल-वर्णीय-लोमचर्मणा अलङ्कृतौ जातौ। एवं तस्य दर्शनात् बर्बर-आढ्यता समचारीत्।    हस्ते मूर्धखोलम् अभूत्। मुखस्य उपरितने अर्ध-भागे गण्डभित्तेः अधः पर्यन्तं कृष्ण-वर्णीय-मृदुक-मुखावरणम् अभूत्। सः मुखावरणस्य समायोजनं कुर्वन् अभूत् इति भाति, यतोहि प्रवेश-समये हस्तः मुखावरणे दृष्टः। मुखस्य अधस्तन-भागे सः दृढस्वभावी इव दृष्टः अभूत्। तस्य अधस्तन-ओष्ठः स्थूलः अभूत्। दीर्घम् ऋजु चुबुकं हठ-स्वभावं सूचवत् अभूत्।</p>
<p>"किं मम पत्रं प्राप्तम्?" इति सः गभीरेण कठोरेण गाढ-जर्मनीयेन स्वरेण अप्राक्षीत्। "दर्शनार्थम् आगमिष्यामि इति अवोचम्" इति उक्त्वा कः सम्बोधनीयः इति अनिश्चितः इव सः आवाम् पर्यायेण अद्राक्षीत्।</p>
<p>आसन्दं स्वीकरोतु इति होम्सः अवोचत्। "मम मित्रं सहकारी साहायकःवाट्सन-भिषक्। भवन्तं दिग्गजं कथम् सम्बोधयेयम्?"</p>
<p>"बोहीमियेयः ठक्कुरः वोन्क्रामः इति मां संबोधयितुं शक्नोति भवान्। अवगच्छामि यत् सः सज्जनः, भवन्मित्रम्, आदरणीयः वाक्संयमी, अतिमहत्त्व-विषये विश्वासार्हः।</p>
<p>निर्गन्तुम् उत्तिष्ठवान् अभूवं किन्तु होम्सः मम मणिबन्धं गृहीत्वा आसन्दे नुदितवान्। "आवौ उभौ उत वा न कश्चिद्।" इति होम्सः अवोचत्। "अस्य सज्जनस्य पुरस्तात् मत्-समक्ष-त्वद्-वचनीयं सर्वं वक्तुं शक्नोति भवान्।"</p>
<p>औदासीन्यं सूचयन् ठक्कुरः स्वस्कन्धौ अकम्पयत्। "अस्तु, आरभ्यताम्! आरम्भात् पूर्वं, वर्षद्वयं यावत् विषयः अयं गुह्यताम् इति प्रतिज्ञा क्रियताम्। वर्षद्वयानन्तरम् अस्य महत्त्वं शून्यं भविष्यति।" इति ठक्कुरः अवोचत्। सम्प्रति 'अस्य विषयस्य तादृशं महत्त्वम् अस्ति यत् युरोपेतिहासेऽपि प्रभावं जनयेत्' इति कथनम् अत्युक्तिर्न भवेत्।”</p>
<p>वचनं ददामि इति होम्सः प्रत्यवोचत्।</p>
<p>"अहमपि।" इति अवोचम्।</p>
<p>""मुखावरण-धारणं क्षम्यताम्।"" इति आवयोः विचित्र-अतिथिः अवोचत्। "सः महनीयः, मम स्वामी, इच्छति यत् मम परिचयः रहसि भवेत्। अपिच मया पूर्वोक्तः उपाधिः मदीयः नास्ति।"</p>
<p>पूर्वमेव ज्ञातं मया इति होम्सः  प्रत्यवोचत्।</p>
<p>"परिस्थितयः विकटाः सन्ति। अतएव सावधानतया व्यवहरे। तं महालोकापवादं निवारयितुम् इच्छामि येन युरोपे विराजमानं प्रमुखं कुटुम्बम् आपदि पातयितुं शक्यते। सङ्क्षेपे वदामि यत् अस्मिन् विषये बोहीमिया-राज-परिवारः ओर्म्ष्टैन-परिवारः संबद्धः अस्ति।" इति अवदत् ठक्कुरः।</p>
<p>"तदपि ज्ञातं मया" इति मन्दस्वरेण उक्त्वा होम्सः आसन्दे ससुखम् उपविश्य नेत्रौ उन्मीलितवान् अभूत्।</p>
<p>युरोपे तीक्ष्णतमः तार्किकः अनलसतमः अन्वेषकः इति वर्णितं म्लानं शिथिलीभूतं नरम् अस्मद्-अभ्यागतः आश्चर्येण अद्राक्षीत्। होम्सः शनैः नेत्रौ उन्मील्य स्वीयं भीमकायं ग्राहकम् अधीरतया अद्राक्षीत्।</p>
<p>"हे राजन्! कृपया भवदीयः समस्यां वर्णयतु भवान् यतोहि भवतः साहाय्यं कर्तुं शक्नोमि इति होम्सः अवोचत्।"</p>
<p>The man sprang from his chair and paced up and down the room in uncontrollable agitation. Then, with a gesture of desperation, he tore the mask from his face and hurled it upon the ground. “You are right,” he cried; “I am the King. Why should I attempt to conceal it?”</p>
<p>“Why, indeed?” murmured Holmes. “Your Majesty had not spoken before I was aware that I was addressing Wilhelm Gottsreich Sigismond von Ormstein, Grand Duke of Cassel-Felstein, and hereditary King of Bohemia.”</p>
<p>“But you can understand,” said our strange visitor, sitting down once more and passing his hand over his high white forehead, “you can understand that I am not accustomed to doing such business in my own person. Yet the matter was so delicate that I could not confide it to an agent without putting myself in his power. I have come incognito from Prague for the purpose of consulting you.”</p>
<p>“Then, pray consult,” said Holmes, shutting his eyes once more.</p>
<p>“The facts are briefly these: Some five years ago, during a lengthy visit to Warsaw, I made the acquaintance of the well-known adventuress, Irene Adler. The name is no doubt familiar to you.”</p>
<p>“Kindly look her up in my index, Doctor,” murmured Holmes without opening his eyes. For many years he had adopted a system of docketing all paragraphs concerning men and things, so that it was difficult to name a subject or a person on which he could not at once furnish information. In this case I found her biography sandwiched in between that of a Hebrew rabbi and that of a staff-commander who had written a monograph upon the deep-sea fishes.</p>
<p>“Let me see!” said Holmes. “Hum! Born in New Jersey in the year 1858. Contralto⁠—hum! La Scala, hum! Prima donna Imperial Opera of Warsaw⁠—yes! Retired from operatic stage⁠—ha! Living in London⁠—quite so! Your Majesty, as I understand, became entangled with this young person, wrote her some compromising letters, and is now desirous of getting those letters back.”</p>
<p>“Precisely so. But how⁠—”</p>
<p>“Was there a secret marriage?”</p>
<p>“None.”</p>
<p>“No legal papers or certificates?”</p>
<p>“None.”</p>
<p>“Then I fail to follow your Majesty. If this young person should produce her letters for blackmailing or other purposes, how is she to prove their authenticity?”</p>
<p>“There is the writing.”</p>
<p>“Pooh, pooh! Forgery.”</p>
<p>“My private notepaper.”</p>
<p>“Stolen.”</p>
<p>“My own seal.”</p>
<p>“Imitated.”</p>
<p>“My photograph.”</p>
<p>“Bought.”</p>
<p>“We were both in the photograph.”</p>
<p>“Oh, dear! That is very bad! Your Majesty has indeed committed an indiscretion.”</p>
<p>“I was mad⁠—insane.”</p>
<p>“You have compromised yourself seriously.”</p>
<p>“I was only Crown Prince then. I was young. I am but thirty now.”</p>
<p>“It must be recovered.”</p>
<p>“We have tried and failed.”</p>
<p>“Your Majesty must pay. It must be bought.”</p>
<p>“She will not sell.”</p>
<p>“Stolen, then.”</p>
<p>“Five attempts have been made. Twice burglars in my pay ransacked her house. Once we diverted her luggage when she travelled. Twice she has been waylaid. There has been no result.”</p>
<p>“No sign of it?”</p>
<p>“Absolutely none.”</p>
<p>Holmes laughed. “It is quite a pretty little problem,” said he.</p>
<p>“But a very serious one to me,” returned the King reproachfully.</p>
<p>“Very, indeed. And what does she propose to do with the photograph?”</p>
<p>“To ruin me.”</p>
<p>“But how?”</p>
<p>“I am about to be married.”</p>
<p>“So I have heard.”</p>
<p>“To Clotilde Lothman von Saxe-Meningen, second daughter of the King of Scandinavia. You may know the strict principles of her family. She is herself the very soul of delicacy. A shadow of a doubt as to my conduct would bring the matter to an end.”</p>
<p>“And Irene Adler?”</p>
<p>“Threatens to send them the photograph. And she will do it. I know that she will do it. You do not know her, but she has a soul of steel. She has the face of the most beautiful of women, and the mind of the most resolute of men. Rather than I should marry another woman, there are no lengths to which she would not go⁠—none.”</p>
<p>“You are sure that she has not sent it yet?”</p>
<p>“I am sure.”</p>
<p>“And why?”</p>
<p>“Because she has said that she would send it on the day when the betrothal was publicly proclaimed. That will be next Monday.”</p>
<p>“Oh, then we have three days yet,” said Holmes with a yawn. “That is very fortunate, as I have one or two matters of importance to look into just at present. Your Majesty will, of course, stay in London for the present?”</p>
<p>“Certainly. You will find me at the Langham under the name of the Count Von Kramm.”</p>
<p>“Then I shall drop you a line to let you know how we progress.”</p>
<p>“Pray do so. I shall be all anxiety.”</p>
<p>“Then, as to money?”</p>
<p>“You have <i>carte blanche</i>.”</p>
<p>“Absolutely?”</p>
<p>“I tell you that I would give one of the provinces of my kingdom to have that photograph.”</p>
<p>“And for present expenses?”</p>
<p>The King took a heavy chamois leather bag from under his cloak and laid it on the table.</p>
<p>“There are three hundred pounds in gold and seven hundred in notes,” he said.</p>
<p>Holmes scribbled a receipt upon a sheet of his notebook and handed it to him.</p>
<p>“And Mademoiselle’s address?” he asked.</p>
<p>“Is Briony Lodge, Serpentine Avenue, St. John’s Wood.”</p>
<p>Holmes took a note of it. “One other question,” said he. “Was the photograph a cabinet?”</p>
<p>“It was.”</p>
<p>“Then, good night, your Majesty, and I trust that we shall soon have some good news for you. And good night, Watson,” he added, as the wheels of the royal brougham rolled down the street. “If you will be good enough to call tomorrow afternoon at three o’clock I should like to chat this little matter over with you.”</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<meta>
<title n="II"/>
</meta>
<p>At three o’clock precisely I was at Baker Street, but Holmes had not yet returned. The landlady informed me that he had left the house shortly after eight o’clock in the morning. I sat down beside the fire, however, with the intention of awaiting him, however long he might be. I was already deeply interested in his inquiry, for, though it was surrounded by none of the grim and strange features which were associated with the two crimes which I have already recorded, still, the nature of the case and the exalted station of his client gave it a character of its own. Indeed, apart from the nature of the investigation which my friend had on hand, there was something in his masterly grasp of a situation, and his keen, incisive reasoning, which made it a pleasure to me to study his system of work, and to follow the quick, subtle methods by which he disentangled the most inextricable mysteries. So accustomed was I to his invariable success that the very possibility of his failing had ceased to enter into my head.</p>
<p>It was close upon four before the door opened, and a drunken-looking groom, ill-kempt and side-whiskered, with an inflamed face and disreputable clothes, walked into the room. Accustomed as I was to my friend’s amazing powers in the use of disguises, I had to look three times before I was certain that it was indeed he. With a nod he vanished into the bedroom, whence he emerged in five minutes tweed-suited and respectable, as of old. Putting his hands into his pockets, he stretched out his legs in front of the fire and laughed heartily for some minutes.</p>
<p>“Well, really!” he cried, and then he choked and laughed again until he was obliged to lie back, limp and helpless, in the chair.</p>
<p>“What is it?”</p>
<p>“It’s quite too funny. I am sure you could never guess how I employed my morning, or what I ended by doing.”</p>
<p>“I can’t imagine. I suppose that you have been watching the habits, and perhaps the house, of Miss Irene Adler.”</p>
<p>“Quite so; but the sequel was rather unusual. I will tell you, however. I left the house a little after eight o’clock this morning in the character of a groom out of work. There is a wonderful sympathy and freemasonry among horsey men. Be one of them, and you will know all that there is to know. I soon found Briony Lodge. It is a <i>bijou</i> villa, with a garden at the back, but built out in front right up to the road, two stories. Chubb lock to the door. Large sitting-room on the right side, well furnished, with long windows almost to the floor, and those preposterous English window fasteners which a child could open. Behind there was nothing remarkable, save that the passage window could be reached from the top of the coach-house. I walked round it and examined it closely from every point of view, but without noting anything else of interest.</p>
<p>“I then lounged down the street and found, as I expected, that there was a mews in a lane which runs down by one wall of the garden. I lent the ostlers a hand in rubbing down their horses, and received in exchange twopence, a glass of half-and-half, two fills of shag tobacco, and as much information as I could desire about Miss Adler, to say nothing of half a dozen other people in the neighbourhood in whom I was not in the least interested, but whose biographies I was compelled to listen to.”</p>
<p>“And what of Irene Adler?” I asked.</p>
<p>“Oh, she has turned all the men’s heads down in that part. She is the daintiest thing under a bonnet on this planet. So say the Serpentine-mews, to a man. She lives quietly, sings at concerts, drives out at five every day, and returns at seven sharp for dinner. Seldom goes out at other times, except when she sings. Has only one male visitor, but a good deal of him. He is dark, handsome, and dashing, never calls less than once a day, and often twice. He is a Mr. Godfrey Norton, of the Inner Temple. See the advantages of a cabman as a confidant. They had driven him home a dozen times from Serpentine-mews, and knew all about him. When I had listened to all they had to tell, I began to walk up and down near Briony Lodge once more, and to think over my plan of campaign.</p>
<p>“This Godfrey Norton was evidently an important factor in the matter. He was a lawyer. That sounded ominous. What was the relation between them, and what the object of his repeated visits? Was she his client, his friend, or his mistress? If the former, she had probably transferred the photograph to his keeping. If the latter, it was less likely. On the issue of this question depended whether I should continue my work at Briony Lodge, or turn my attention to the gentleman’s chambers in the Temple. It was a delicate point, and it widened the field of my inquiry. I fear that I bore you with these details, but I have to let you see my little difficulties, if you are to understand the situation.”</p>
<p>“I am following you closely,” I answered.</p>
<p>“I was still balancing the matter in my mind when a hansom cab drove up to Briony Lodge, and a gentleman sprang out. He was a remarkably handsome man, dark, aquiline, and moustached⁠—evidently the man of whom I had heard. He appeared to be in a great hurry, shouted to the cabman to wait, and brushed past the maid who opened the door with the air of a man who was thoroughly at home.</p>
<p>“He was in the house about half an hour, and I could catch glimpses of him in the windows of the sitting-room, pacing up and down, talking excitedly, and waving his arms. Of her I could see nothing. Presently he emerged, looking even more flurried than before. As he stepped up to the cab, he pulled a gold watch from his pocket and looked at it earnestly, ‘Drive like the devil,’ he shouted, ‘first to Gross &amp; Hankey’s in Regent Street, and then to the Church of St. Monica in the Edgeware Road. Half a guinea if you do it in twenty minutes!’</p>
<p>“Away they went, and I was just wondering whether I should not do well to follow them when up the lane came a neat little landau, the coachman with his coat only half-buttoned, and his tie under his ear, while all the tags of his harness were sticking out of the buckles. It hadn’t pulled up before she shot out of the hall door and into it. I only caught a glimpse of her at the moment, but she was a lovely woman, with a face that a man might die for.</p>
<p>“ ‘The Church of St. Monica, John,’ she cried, ‘and half a sovereign if you reach it in twenty minutes.’</p>
<p>“This was quite too good to lose, Watson. I was just balancing whether I should run for it, or whether I should perch behind her landau when a cab came through the street. The driver looked twice at such a shabby fare, but I jumped in before he could object. ‘The Church of St. Monica,’ said I, ‘and half a sovereign if you reach it in twenty minutes.’ It was twenty-five minutes to twelve, and of course it was clear enough what was in the wind.</p>
<p>“My cabby drove fast. I don’t think I ever drove faster, but the others were there before us. The cab and the landau with their steaming horses were in front of the door when I arrived. I paid the man and hurried into the church. There was not a soul there save the two whom I had followed and a surpliced clergyman, who seemed to be expostulating with them. They were all three standing in a knot in front of the altar. I lounged up the side aisle like any other idler who has dropped into a church. Suddenly, to my surprise, the three at the altar faced round to me, and Godfrey Norton came running as hard as he could towards me.</p>
<p>“ ‘Thank God,’ he cried. ‘You’ll do. Come! Come!’</p>
<p>“ ‘What then?’ I asked.</p>
<p>“ ‘Come, man, come, only three minutes, or it won’t be legal.’</p>
<p>“I was half-dragged up to the altar, and before I knew where I was I found myself mumbling responses which were whispered in my ear, and vouching for things of which I knew nothing, and generally assisting in the secure tying up of Irene Adler, spinster, to Godfrey Norton, bachelor. It was all done in an instant, and there was the gentleman thanking me on the one side and the lady on the other, while the clergyman beamed on me in front. It was the most preposterous position in which I ever found myself in my life, and it was the thought of it that started me laughing just now. It seems that there had been some informality about their license, that the clergyman absolutely refused to marry them without a witness of some sort, and that my lucky appearance saved the bridegroom from having to sally out into the streets in search of a best man. The bride gave me a sovereign, and I mean to wear it on my watch chain in memory of the occasion.”</p>
<p>“This is a very unexpected turn of affairs,” said I; “and what then?”</p>
<p>“Well, I found my plans very seriously menaced. It looked as if the pair might take an immediate departure, and so necessitate very prompt and energetic measures on my part. At the church door, however, they separated, he driving back to the Temple, and she to her own house. ‘I shall drive out in the park at five as usual,’ she said as she left him. I heard no more. They drove away in different directions, and I went off to make my own arrangements.”</p>
<p>“Which are?”</p>
<p>“Some cold beef and a glass of beer,” he answered, ringing the bell. “I have been too busy to think of food, and I am likely to be busier still this evening. By the way, Doctor, I shall want your cooperation.”</p>
<p>“I shall be delighted.”</p>
<p>“You don’t mind breaking the law?”</p>
<p>“Not in the least.”</p>
<p>“Nor running a chance of arrest?”</p>
<p>“Not in a good cause.”</p>
<p>“Oh, the cause is excellent!”</p>
<p>“Then I am your man.”</p>
<p>“I was sure that I might rely on you.”</p>
<p>“But what is it you wish?”</p>
<p>“When Mrs. Turner has brought in the tray I will make it clear to you. Now,” he said as he turned hungrily on the simple fare that our landlady had provided, “I must discuss it while I eat, for I have not much time. It is nearly five now. In two hours we must be on the scene of action. Miss Irene, or Madame, rather, returns from her drive at seven. We must be at Briony Lodge to meet her.”</p>
<p>“And what then?”</p>
<p>“You must leave that to me. I have already arranged what is to occur. There is only one point on which I must insist. You must not interfere, come what may. You understand?”</p>
<p>“I am to be neutral?”</p>
<p>“To do nothing whatever. There will probably be some small unpleasantness. Do not join in it. It will end in my being conveyed into the house. Four or five minutes afterwards the sitting-room window will open. You are to station yourself close to that open window.”</p>
<p>“Yes.”</p>
<p>“You are to watch me, for I will be visible to you.”</p>
<p>“Yes.”</p>
<p>“And when I raise my hand⁠—so⁠—you will throw into the room what I give you to throw, and will, at the same time, raise the cry of fire. You quite follow me?”</p>
<p>“Entirely.”</p>
<p>“It is nothing very formidable,” he said, taking a long cigar-shaped roll from his pocket. “It is an ordinary plumber’s smoke-rocket, fitted with a cap at either end to make it self-lighting. Your task is confined to that. When you raise your cry of fire, it will be taken up by quite a number of people. You may then walk to the end of the street, and I will rejoin you in ten minutes. I hope that I have made myself clear?”</p>
<p>“I am to remain neutral, to get near the window, to watch you, and at the signal to throw in this object, then to raise the cry of fire, and to wait you at the corner of the street.”</p>
<p>“Precisely.”</p>
<p>“Then you may entirely rely on me.”</p>
<p>“That is excellent. I think, perhaps, it is almost time that I prepare for the new role I have to play.”</p>
<p>He disappeared into his bedroom and returned in a few minutes in the character of an amiable and simple-minded Nonconformist clergyman. His broad black hat, his baggy trousers, his white tie, his sympathetic smile, and general look of peering and benevolent curiosity were such as Mr. John Hare alone could have equalled. It was not merely that Holmes changed his costume. His expression, his manner, his very soul seemed to vary with every fresh part that he assumed. The stage lost a fine actor, even as science lost an acute reasoner, when he became a specialist in crime.</p>
<p>It was a quarter past six when we left Baker Street, and it still wanted ten minutes to the hour when we found ourselves in Serpentine Avenue. It was already dusk, and the lamps were just being lighted as we paced up and down in front of Briony Lodge, waiting for the coming of its occupant. The house was just such as I had pictured it from Sherlock Holmes’ succinct description, but the locality appeared to be less private than I expected. On the contrary, for a small street in a quiet neighbourhood, it was remarkably animated. There was a group of shabbily dressed men smoking and laughing in a corner, a scissors-grinder with his wheel, two guardsmen who were flirting with a nurse-girl, and several well-dressed young men who were lounging up and down with cigars in their mouths.</p>
<p>“You see,” remarked Holmes, as we paced to and fro in front of the house, “this marriage rather simplifies matters. The photograph becomes a double-edged weapon now. The chances are that she would be as averse to its being seen by Mr. Godfrey Norton, as our client is to its coming to the eyes of his princess. Now the question is, where are we to find the photograph?”</p>
<p>“Where, indeed?”</p>
<p>“It is most unlikely that she carries it about with her. It is cabinet size. Too large for easy concealment about a woman’s dress. She knows that the King is capable of having her waylaid and searched. Two attempts of the sort have already been made. We may take it, then, that she does not carry it about with her.”</p>
<p>“Where, then?”</p>
<p>“Her banker or her lawyer. There is that double possibility. But I am inclined to think neither. Women are naturally secretive, and they like to do their own secreting. Why should she hand it over to anyone else? She could trust her own guardianship, but she could not tell what indirect or political influence might be brought to bear upon a business man. Besides, remember that she had resolved to use it within a few days. It must be where she can lay her hands upon it. It must be in her own house.”</p>
<p>“But it has twice been burgled.”</p>
<p>“Pshaw! They did not know how to look.”</p>
<p>“But how will you look?”</p>
<p>“I will not look.”</p>
<p>“What then?”</p>
<p>“I will get her to show me.”</p>
<p>“But she will refuse.”</p>
<p>“She will not be able to. But I hear the rumble of wheels. It is her carriage. Now carry out my orders to the letter.”</p>
<p>As he spoke the gleam of the sidelights of a carriage came round the curve of the avenue. It was a smart little landau which rattled up to the door of Briony Lodge. As it pulled up, one of the loafing men at the corner dashed forward to open the door in the hope of earning a copper, but was elbowed away by another loafer, who had rushed up with the same intention. A fierce quarrel broke out, which was increased by the two guardsmen, who took sides with one of the loungers, and by the scissors-grinder, who was equally hot upon the other side. A blow was struck, and in an instant the lady, who had stepped from her carriage, was the centre of a little knot of flushed and struggling men, who struck savagely at each other with their fists and sticks. Holmes dashed into the crowd to protect the lady; but, just as he reached her, he gave a cry and dropped to the ground, with the blood running freely down his face. At his fall the guardsmen took to their heels in one direction and the loungers in the other, while a number of better dressed people, who had watched the scuffle without taking part in it, crowded in to help the lady and to attend to the injured man. Irene Adler, as I will still call her, had hurried up the steps; but she stood at the top with her superb figure outlined against the lights of the hall, looking back into the street.</p>
<p>“Is the poor gentleman much hurt?” she asked.</p>
<p>“He is dead,” cried several voices.</p>
<p>“No, no, there’s life in him!” shouted another. “But he’ll be gone before you can get him to hospital.”</p>
<p>“He’s a brave fellow,” said a woman. “They would have had the lady’s purse and watch if it hadn’t been for him. They were a gang, and a rough one, too. Ah, he’s breathing now.”</p>
<p>“He can’t lie in the street. May we bring him in, marm?”</p>
<p>“Surely. Bring him into the sitting-room. There is a comfortable sofa. This way, please!”</p>
<p>Slowly and solemnly he was borne into Briony Lodge and laid out in the principal room, while I still observed the proceedings from my post by the window. The lamps had been lit, but the blinds had not been drawn, so that I could see Holmes as he lay upon the couch. I do not know whether he was seized with compunction at that moment for the part he was playing, but I know that I never felt more heartily ashamed of myself in my life than when I saw the beautiful creature against whom I was conspiring, or the grace and kindliness with which she waited upon the injured man. And yet it would be the blackest treachery to Holmes to draw back now from the part which he had entrusted to me. I hardened my heart, and took the smoke-rocket from under my ulster. After all, I thought, we are not injuring her. We are but preventing her from injuring another.</p>
<p>Holmes had sat up upon the couch, and I saw him motion like a man who is in need of air. A maid rushed across and threw open the window. At the same instant I saw him raise his hand and at the signal I tossed my rocket into the room with a cry of “Fire!” The word was no sooner out of my mouth than the whole crowd of spectators, well dressed and ill⁠—gentlemen, ostlers, and servant maids⁠—joined in a general shriek of “Fire!” Thick clouds of smoke curled through the room and out at the open window. I caught a glimpse of rushing figures, and a moment later the voice of Holmes from within assuring them that it was a false alarm. Slipping through the shouting crowd I made my way to the corner of the street, and in ten minutes was rejoiced to find my friend’s arm in mine, and to get away from the scene of uproar. He walked swiftly and in silence for some few minutes until we had turned down one of the quiet streets which lead towards the Edgeware Road.</p>
<p>“You did it very nicely, Doctor,” he remarked. “Nothing could have been better. It is all right.”</p>
<p>“You have the photograph?”</p>
<p>“I know where it is.”</p>
<p>“And how did you find out?”</p>
<p>“She showed me, as I told you she would.”</p>
<p>“I am still in the dark.”</p>
<p>“I do not wish to make a mystery,” said he, laughing. “The matter was perfectly simple. You, of course, saw that everyone in the street was an accomplice. They were all engaged for the evening.”</p>
<p>“I guessed as much.”</p>
<p>“Then, when the row broke out, I had a little moist red paint in the palm of my hand. I rushed forward, fell down, clapped my hand to my face, and became a piteous spectacle. It is an old trick.”</p>
<p>“That also I could fathom.”</p>
<p>“Then they carried me in. She was bound to have me in. What else could she do? And into her sitting-room, which was the very room which I suspected. It lay between that and her bedroom, and I was determined to see which. They laid me on a couch, I motioned for air, they were compelled to open the window, and you had your chance.”</p>
<p>“How did that help you?”</p>
<p>“It was all-important. When a woman thinks that her house is on fire, her instinct is at once to rush to the thing which she values most. It is a perfectly overpowering impulse, and I have more than once taken advantage of it. In the case of the Darlington Substitution Scandal it was of use to me, and also in the Arnsworth Castle business. A married woman grabs at her baby; an unmarried one reaches for her jewel-box. Now it was clear to me that our lady of today had nothing in the house more precious to her than what we are in quest of. She would rush to secure it. The alarm of fire was admirably done. The smoke and shouting were enough to shake nerves of steel. She responded beautifully. The photograph is in a recess behind a sliding panel just above the right bellpull. She was there in an instant, and I caught a glimpse of it as she half drew it out. When I cried out that it was a false alarm, she replaced it, glanced at the rocket, rushed from the room, and I have not seen her since. I rose, and, making my excuses, escaped from the house. I hesitated whether to attempt to secure the photograph at once; but the coachman had come in, and as he was watching me narrowly, it seemed safer to wait. A little over-precipitance may ruin all.”</p>
<p>“And now?” I asked.</p>
<p>“Our quest is practically finished. I shall call with the King tomorrow, and with you, if you care to come with us. We will be shown into the sitting-room to wait for the lady, but it is probable that when she comes she may find neither us nor the photograph. It might be a satisfaction to his Majesty to regain it with his own hands.”</p>
<p>“And when will you call?”</p>
<p>“At eight in the morning. She will not be up, so that we shall have a clear field. Besides, we must be prompt, for this marriage may mean a complete change in her life and habits. I must wire to the King without delay.”</p>
<p>We had reached Baker Street and had stopped at the door. He was searching his pockets for the key when someone passing said:</p>
<p>“Good night, Mister Sherlock Holmes.”</p>
<p>There were several people on the pavement at the time, but the greeting appeared to come from a slim youth in an ulster who had hurried by.</p>
<p>“I’ve heard that voice before,” said Holmes, staring down the dimly lit street. “Now, I wonder who the deuce that could have been.”</p>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<meta>
<title n="III"/>
</meta>
<p>I slept at Baker Street that night, and we were engaged upon our toast and coffee in the morning when the King of Bohemia rushed into the room.</p>
<p>“You have really got it!” he cried, grasping Sherlock Holmes by either shoulder and looking eagerly into his face.</p>
<p>“Not yet.”</p>
<p>“But you have hopes?”</p>
<p>“I have hopes.”</p>
<p>“Then, come. I am all impatience to be gone.”</p>
<p>“We must have a cab.”</p>
<p>“No, my brougham is waiting.”</p>
<p>“Then that will simplify matters.” We descended and started off once more for Briony Lodge.</p>
<p>“Irene Adler is married,” remarked Holmes.</p>
<p>“Married! When?”</p>
<p>“Yesterday.”</p>
<p>“But to whom?”</p>
<p>“To an English lawyer named Norton.”</p>
<p>“But she could not love him.”</p>
<p>“I am in hopes that she does.”</p>
<p>“And why in hopes?”</p>
<p>“Because it would spare your Majesty all fear of future annoyance. If the lady loves her husband, she does not love your Majesty. If she does not love your Majesty, there is no reason why she should interfere with your Majesty’s plan.”</p>
<p>“It is true. And yet⁠—! Well! I wish she had been of my own station! What a queen she would have made!” He relapsed into a moody silence, which was not broken until we drew up in Serpentine Avenue.</p>
<p>The door of Briony Lodge was open, and an elderly woman stood upon the steps. She watched us with a sardonic eye as we stepped from the brougham.</p>
<p>“Mr. Sherlock Holmes, I believe?” said she.</p>
<p>“I am Mr. Holmes,” answered my companion, looking at her with a questioning and rather startled gaze.</p>
<p>“Indeed! My mistress told me that you were likely to call. She left this morning with her husband by the 5:15 train from Charing Cross for the Continent.”</p>
<p>“What!” Sherlock Holmes staggered back, white with chagrin and surprise. “Do you mean that she has left England?”</p>
<p>“Never to return.”</p>
<p>“And the papers?” asked the King hoarsely. “All is lost.”</p>
<p>“We shall see.” He pushed past the servant and rushed into the drawing-room, followed by the King and myself. The furniture was scattered about in every direction, with dismantled shelves and open drawers, as if the lady had hurriedly ransacked them before her flight. Holmes rushed at the bellpull, tore back a small sliding shutter, and, plunging in his hand, pulled out a photograph and a letter. The photograph was of Irene Adler herself in evening dress, the letter was superscribed to “Sherlock Holmes, Esq. To be left till called for.” My friend tore it open, and we all three read it together. It was dated at midnight of the preceding night and ran in this way:</p>
<letter>
<p>“<span>My Dear <span>Mr. Sherlock Holmes</span></span>⁠—You really did it very well. You took me in completely. Until after the alarm of fire, I had not a suspicion. But then, when I found how I had betrayed myself, I began to think. I had been warned against you months ago. I had been told that, if the King employed an agent, it would certainly be you. And your address had been given me. Yet, with all this, you made me reveal what you wanted to know. Even after I became suspicious, I found it hard to think evil of such a dear, kind old clergyman. But, you know, I have been trained as an actress myself. Male costume is nothing new to me. I often take advantage of the freedom which it gives. I sent John, the coachman, to watch you, ran upstairs, got into my walking clothes, as I call them, and came down just as you departed.</p>
<p>“Well, I followed you to your door, and so made sure that I was really an object of interest to the celebrated Mr. Sherlock Holmes. Then I, rather imprudently, wished you good night, and started for the Temple to see my husband.</p>
<p>“We both thought the best resource was flight, when pursued by so formidable an antagonist; so you will find the nest empty when you call tomorrow. As to the photograph, your client may rest in peace. I love and am loved by a better man than he. The King may do what he will without hindrance from one whom he has cruelly wronged. I keep it only to safeguard myself, and to preserve a weapon which will always secure me from any steps which he might take in the future. I leave a photograph which he might care to possess; and I remain, dear Mr. Sherlock Holmes,</p>
<footer role="presentation">
<p>“Very truly yours,</p>
<p>“Irene Norton, <i>née</i> Adler.”</p>
</footer>
</letter>
<p>“What a woman⁠—oh, what a woman!” cried the King of Bohemia, when we had all three read this epistle. “Did I not tell you how quick and resolute she was? Would she not have made an admirable queen? Is it not a pity that she was not on my level?”</p>
<p>“From what I have seen of the lady, she seems, indeed, to be on a very different level to your Majesty,” said Holmes coldly. “I am sorry that I have not been able to bring your Majesty’s business to a more successful conclusion.”</p>
<p>“On the contrary, my dear sir,” cried the King; “nothing could be more successful. I know that her word is inviolate. The photograph is now as safe as if it were in the fire.”</p>
<p>“I am glad to hear your Majesty say so.”</p>
<p>“I am immensely indebted to you. Pray tell me in what way I can reward you. This ring⁠—” He slipped an emerald snake ring from his finger and held it out upon the palm of his hand.</p>
<p>“Your Majesty has something which I should value even more highly,” said Holmes.</p>
<p>“You have but to name it.”</p>
<p>“This photograph!”</p>
<p>The King stared at him in amazement.</p>
<p>“Irene’s photograph!” he cried. “Certainly, if you wish it.”</p>
<p>“I thank your Majesty. Then there is no more to be done in the matter. I have the honour to wish you a very good morning.” He bowed, and, turning away without observing the hand which the King had stretched out to him, he set off in my company for his chambers.</p>
<hr/>
<p>And that was how a great scandal threatened to affect the kingdom of Bohemia, and how the best plans of Mr. Sherlock Holmes were beaten by a woman’s wit. He used to make merry over the cleverness of women, but I have not heard him do it of late. And when he speaks of Irene Adler, or when he refers to her photograph, it is always under the honourable title of <em>the</em> woman.</p>
</chapter>
</chapter>
</document>